# 大家好
Hi everyone!
# 大個門都已經被那個小狗哇
The gate was already damaged by the, you know, the puppies,
# 被爬壞啦
always climbed the gate.
# 所以現在
So now,
# 現在我們叫兄弟過來 裝一下這個門
now we've asked our buddies to come over, and have the new gate installed.
# 這裝上去就很好看啦
It will look really nice when it's done.
# 現在快裝好一扇啦
Now one is nearly done.
# 還要對好位甲置
They still need to match the positions.
# 對好位就裝好啦 裝好就很好看啦
Then it will be done and it will look really nice.
# 到時就裡面 裡面就看不到的 看王到裡面的
Then the inside, the inside can' be seen, can't be seen from outside.
# 今天天氣比較冷啦 你看
Today is rather cold. Look!
# 小狗都靠著它
The puppies are leaning on her,
# 它奶奶 它老媽在睡覺
sleeping next to their grandma, their mother.
# 你看 這個鐵門已經裝好啦
Look! The gate is now installed.
# 這很漂亮哦
It's really pretty.
# 看不到裡面啦
The inside can't be seen.
# 把門關起來就看不到裡面啦
The inside can't be seen when the gate is closed.
# 小狗也跑不出來啦
And the doggies can't run away.
# 小狗它們也跑不出來啦
The doggies can no longer run away.
# 這個
This is,
# 紅象草哦
red elephant grass, you know.
# 我們拿到田裡面去種一些這紅象草來
Let's take it to the field and plant some red elephant grass.
# 我們這有幾棵 其它地方我都沒種
I have just a few here, and nowhere else.
# 我把它種多一點 現在都長嫩芽啦
Let's plant a bit more. They have already started sprouting.
# 這有好多嫩芽
Here are a lot of sprouts.
# 全長嫩芽啦
All have already started sprouting.
# 你看 都長嫩芽啦 一節一節的
Look! It's already sprouting. Look at the joints.
# 我們插上去它就會生啦
It will start growing once we stick it in.
# 插到田裡面去
I mean, stick it into the field.
# 原來就是一棵的 現在長那麼多
There was only one at the beginning. But now there are so many.
# 今年又把這些種下去的話
After planting all these this year,
# 幾百棵 幾千棵都出來啦
it might become hundreds, or thousands of them.
# 跑小朋友
No running, kid!
# 還那麼小你就亂跑
You're still a kid but you're already running here and there.
# 把這些丟到車上去
Let me throw all these onto the car.
# 你看 把它扛那麼個 荒地裡面去種
Look! I'm taking them to the abandoned field and have them planted there.
# 在前面
It's just in front of us.
# 這一片都是荒的 都是雜草
This whole area is abandoned. There are only weeds.
# 但是這個草長起來的話 這個雜草就會死掉的
But the weeds would die out once the grass starts growing.
# 種這個很簡單的 就這樣
Planting it is a no-brainer. That's it.
# 這幾節
These chunks,
# 隨便插 插在這附近
simply stick them in, anywhere nearby.
# 插下去 插下穩這裡
Stick it in. It's shaky here.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one,
# 這種就是插在這
this one needs to be stuck into,
# 有泥土的地方就插在泥土上去
into the soil, if there's soil.
# 如果沒泥土的話
If there's no soil,
# 就是用鋤頭
then I need a hoe.
# 把這個插下去就好啦
Stick it in, and it's done.
# 這個象草也可以鞏固那個水土流失哦 (註︰應該是「鞏固泥土防止水土流失」吧)
The elephant grass can also stabilize the soil and prevent it from being washed away.
# 這個大水一沖的話 有這個根話
The roots of the grass can catch the, well, the soil,
# 就把那個 沙土哇 留住
when the river overflows.
# 如果沒有這個的話 它就很容易把這個土掀掉
Without the roots, the soil would be easily peeled off,
# 沖到下面去
and washed away.
# 我在附近插一下
Let me stick a few more nearby.
# 你看 這河邊還有薄荷哦
Look! There are also mints on the riverside.
# 這個薄荷是
The mint is...
# 哇 好濃的薄荷味
Wa! A rich scent of mint!
# 是上 上遊 應該上遊沖下來這個根 就在這裡
is up, upstream, it should be washed down from the upstream, and then the roots,
# 生根發芽 那麼大一片
the roots sprouted here. There are so many of them.
# 下次我們摘點田螺來炒
Next time let's get some river snails and fry with the mint.
# 薄荷炒田螺
River snails fried with mint
# 很好吃的哦
Tasty!
# 你看 這個
Look! Here!
# 很漂亮的哦 這個薄荷
The mints are really pretty, you know.
# 這裡還好多艾草哦 這裡
Here's also a lot of mugwort, here.
# 旁邊插一棵下去
Let me stick one next to it,
# 這附近也可以
and also somewhere nearby.
# 這個是黑麥草哦
This is ryegrass.
# 這個餵魚 那魚很喜歡吃的 很嫩的這個
It can be used to feed the fish. The fish like it very much. It's really young.
# 你看 一搞就斷掉
Look! It can be easily torn.
# 而且特別有那種香味
And it also has a particularly strong scent,
# 那種植物的香味
scent of plant.
# 這裡
Here!
# 旁邊 插一棵下去
Let me stick one next to it.
# 這好多這個
There are a lot of, you know,
# 但是現在
eagle ferns.
# 現在等下 等下我來摘
But now...
# 把這個種好了再說
Not now, I'll pick them in a moment.
# 快下雨啦 你看 天都下雨啦
I'll have them all planted first.
# 我摘點那個牛尾節回去
It's gonna rain soon. Look! It starts raining.
# 回去炒
Let me get some eagle ferns back,
# 家裡沒 沒得青菜吃啦
and have them fried.
# 看看這 好多哇
I've run, run out of veggies at home.
# 摘到嫩的來
Look at here! There are a lot!
# 好嫩啊
Let me pick the young ones.
# 好多好嫩的 剛長出來的
They're really young.
# 你看
Many have just grown out from the soil, and are really young.
# 這樣就很好吃的哦
Look!
# 這是野菜
It will then be really tasty.
# 這個也叫野菜
This is wild veggie.
# 你看 這兩個就很嫩的
It's also called wild veggie.
# 你看 摘了那麼一點點
Look! These two are really young.
# 回去啦 夠一餐
Look! I've picked just a tiny little bit here.
# Let's go back. It's enough for a meal.